What we noticed quicker than anything
before is how how much the app has been
promoted by our users, not even by
ourselves. Like every time someone
mentioned App Store Connect in on
Twitter, people would just tag Helm and
say just use Helm instead. And that's
the best feeling you can have, I think.
Welcome to Launched. I'm Charlie Chapman
and today I'm excited to bring you the
developers behind Helm, the outstanding
developer tool for accessing App Store
Connect. Paul Pia and Ha Vanderplug.
guys. Welcome back to the show.
>> Hey, thank you.
>> Yeah, thank you for having us.
>> Uh, Ha has been a previous guest a long
long time ago talking about is it Pey
your uh Apple Watch app.
>> Uh, and then both of you were on the
show. Uh we did a live show at WWDC uh
last year which we recorded. It was very
exciting. Uh Ha got to launch a t-shirt
cannon into the crowd. Both of you ate
cake. Is that right?
>> Coffee cake. Uh it was the one year
anniversary of of Helm.
>> Ah it was the one year anniversary of
Helm. That's right. Yeah. So uh I'm
excited to get into this um because I
think this is the type of app that's
directly aimed at exactly all the people
listening. And on that note, I've been
trying to kick off this show now by
doing a quick elevator pitch of the app
we're talking about. That way, we don't
get into all the details before we even
explain what it is. And so, uh, Paul,
I'm going to have you do just a quick
elevator pitch for what Helm is.
>> Yeah, Helm is a Mac OS and iOS, uh, app
that basically allows you to do a lot of
actions in App Store Connect. I don't
like saying that it's just a client for
App Store Connect because we do quite a
lot uh more. The mission with Helm is to
basically put all the frustrations and
pain points that we had when shipping
our apps and and updates in App Store
Connect and basically fix them like one
at a time, making like the best possible
experience for every single features
that that we come up with um in the app.
The goal essentially is to make it as
easy as possible to um launch your app,
give you the best chance at success, at
getting past uh the review process,
giving you the best chance at like ASO,
um auto translating your content so that
you basically don't don't have to either
hire someone and you can do it in just
like one click. And yeah, there's quite
a lot of of stuff that we've got um in
the in the road map, but the long and
short of it is basically give you the
best experience at shipping your
applications. So you don't basically
have to go through through App Store
Connect. You just go through through
Helm.
>> Anybody listening who uh who has an app
on the App Store knows the pain of using
App Store Connect. It's such a strange
piece of software uh that web app. And
so yeah, using Helm is like it feels
especially for Apple developers, it
feels it feels like being at home to
start off the conversation like we
normally do with the show. Uh I want to
introduce everybody to who you are and
uh hit obviously people can go back and
listen to that whole episode if they
want to. Uh so we're just going to spend
zero time on you. No, I'm kidding. But
uh but I will start with Paul. So, uh,
I'll just ask you the the three
questions that
>> pitch
>> the elevator pitch go make a couple
>> very long elevators in Spain though.
Remember that. Remember that.
>> Uh, but no, the three questions I always
ask is where are you from? Uh, do you
have a formal education related to what
you do? And then what were you doing
before you started working on on Helm
with Ha?
>> Yeah. So, I am originally from Barcelona
in Spain, but I live in the in the UK.
I've lived in the UK for about 11 12
years now. I don't have formal
education. I have a uni degree in
electronic engineering but not in iOS or
anything related to programming. I was
basically just doing analog uh circuitry
and stuff at uni. So nothing to do um
with with what I do at the moment. And
what was I doing before? I was a
software engineer. I think my background
and my career. Um, since I left uni has
been on software and and iOS. Uh, and
then he and I became friends through
conferences and stuff. Then he moved
eventually moved to Manchester and we
started working together on Now Playing
and one thing led to another and
eventually made Helm together.
>> So you were working on stuff together.
Was that in like a sort of contracting
role? cuz now playing is an app I think
of as in hit's sort of catalog of apps.
>> I started now playing by myself. Um and
then like Paul said we met at a
conference became friends real quickly
and we both had the same nerdy
enthusiasm about music and also I know
Paul had a lot more technical capability
than I have to make things like more
performant and stuff because in the end
I'm still a designer turn developer.
It's fine but like not as trained as
Paul. So I was like hey just wanna do
you want to just come in and do this
together? Not as a contracting
necessarily just u share cuts basically
share the pie I guess
>> that was with now playing. So that one
was also kind of a joint uh joint effort
then.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And that's how we started
working together. And then I was doing
full-time indie development at that
point. And as an indie deaf, you ship a
lot of updates. And as everyone else, I
was no longer wanted I was like, I don't
want to deal with this website anymore.
And then I looked at what was there. And
there were a few App Store Connect
clients, but they they weren't really
like up to what I had in mind or what I
wanted from a client. Uh, and then I
started the project, looked at the APO
connect API and it was like Paul,
please help if you want to do this
together.
>> Okay, I want to pull on that thread a
little bit more, but first I guess
really quick,
>> the same questions for you like you know
what's your what's your background
education wise and then what were you
doing uh oh, where are you from and then
what were you doing kind of before you
guys you guys met?
>> Yeah, so I'm from the Netherlands. Um,
lived most of my adult life in
Amsterdam. have been trained as like a
designer originally like a visual
designer. I worked on a lot of different
apps at agencies and then joined a web
product for a long time. Became the head
of design there. That became too big.
Didn't like it. And I also always like
doing mobile apps better than web
products. And then at some point I
always had all these ideas and I was
like how hard can it be to build it
myself cuz otherwise I have to make my
ideas enthusiastic to others. And I
didn't want that cuz that's quite
difficult. I mean it's called pitching
for a reason I guess. And then I was
like well it took me quite a long time.
Then this was around when Swift came
out. I was like oh finally this is
legible cuz I tried a few times with
Objective C and that was impossible to
me. And then with Swift I actually ride
the wave of Swift development a little
bit.
>> Were you in on like those first really
uh shaky versions?
>> Yeah. Oh man.
>> And that you think that's tough when you
when you know development. I started
doing multiple new apps because the
project didn't compile anymore. So,
>> okay.
>> And now we're all back to doing the same
thing with vibe coding, right? As soon
as it breaks, you're just like, "All
right, let's just start over."
>> But now you asked AI to fix it for you,
I guess.
>> That's true. Yeah, that's true. I don't
know. I've gotten it where it's like far
enough along that I'm just like, "Ah,
whatever. Just start Greenfield." So,
that's how you got into doing your own
indie apps. And then you like I don't
remember what your first one was, but
you you kind of got into a pattern of
like you were putting out a bunch of
different apps and eventually that kind
of took over and that became your
full-time gig for a while, right? My
first one was a simple weight tracking
app because health kit was just launched
and I think uh it was quite cumbersome
to put in a new weight measurement and I
was like oh this is maybe a good good
project to learn work with different
Apple APIs and then I did a whole bunch
of different apps like none of them is
like even remotely the same I think cuz
like there's a goal tracking app there's
a music app there's a kite surfering app
I don't even kite surf but hey it taught
me a lot about core motion and stuff.
Even machine learning as well. So, and I
think PT also happened which was like a
chat GPT rapper for Apple Watch which
took off like crazy. But I think for me
it was always just try to do as many
different projects and not to stick too
much to one topic just to learn new
things and I learned a lot from all of
those like different things from all of
the projects I guess.
>> And that what that became a like
sustainable
sort of job for a while.
>> Yeah. Sometimes I filled it up with some
client work like did like
>> UI engineering I guess cuz I was still
designer that knew how to code so it was
quite easy to help other apps as well to
build nice nice little things but I
tried to minimize the amount of client
work that I took on as much as possible.
I only took on clients that I really
really liked.
>> So the origin of Helm then was
you like many of us listening found app
store connect painful to use. you were
like, there should be a better way to do
this. A Mac app feels like obvious
because developers are obviously working
on the Mac and it's kind of a big lots
of different input fields and stuff type
function that you need to do.
>> Yeah.
>> And then like
>> it's a professional tool in a way. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And then like you said like
once you started digging into the APIs
necessary to to create those uh you
realized this is going to be a little
heavy and that's when you reached out to
to Paul.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think quite quickly
because the API itself, this is my
experience. I think Paul has a different
look on it obviously, but I think the
API itself is really really tough to get
like to get the standards, but one I
think once you get it, it's okay. Still
a lot of things are weird, but it's a
really opinionated API in how it's
structured, I would say. And I always
thought this is the reason why it's so
slow on web as well, but it turns out
it's actually not that slow. It's just
different,
>> I think. Yeah, I think they have to
accommodate like a a massive number of
old apps as well and they have to power
like a lot of things that maybe they're
not like as relevant if you use like the
API for like very very small things and
like just to to do quick things. But it
is incredibly complex to get into and to
to make sense of it. But once you do and
you start like understanding how it
works and all that stuff like it's very
very powerful like you can pretty much
do anything on the except like there's
some exceptions but you can basically do
anything the app store connect does just
programmatically with with the API
>> and it's not really designed for your
purposes right like the idea isn't oh
this is an API where you can build
>> a client that replicates what app store
connect does right the the main purpose
is all these people doing heavy
automations or something like that,
right?
>> I think once you start using it for how
we use it, you hit like certain things
where you go like, "Oh, why is this not
available?" And a lot of the times the
answer is like it's not how it was like
initially intended to to like be used.
Um, and we've had like some
conversations as well with like the App
Store Connect API team in labs and all
that stuff and they're always like super
open to like adding more features and
there's been like quite a lot of work.
But you do you do eventually like get to
those points where you think like, "Oh
yeah, maybe this is not what it was we
was built for." And you get like some
hiccups in the API, but the team are
like incredibly open to to this feedback
and and just building on more more
endpoints and stuff.
>> And I think that's an interesting point,
too. If if you aren't already familiar
with Helm, you might assume that this is
kind of uh adversarial to App Store
Connect and that this would be the type
of thing you have to download from some
GitHub repo and build yourself or
something like that. But you've done all
of this completely compliant within
Apple's rules and it's available on the
Mac App Store
>> where you even being featured.
>> Yeah. And and been featured. Right.
Exactly. So it's I feel like that
relationship is actually good and like
you just described like they're open to
that. Was that one of your
driving things from the beginning was
like we want to do this in a like fully
compliant way?
>> Yeah, I think we we always said that we
always really deeply care about setting
a good relationship with Apple still
like we don't want to make them look bad
necessarily. We just want to show them
that there's actually a need for this.
And also same practices like we try to
keep privacy in mind and stuff and
things like that. But everything we do
make it as accessible as possible and
all those same norms in what app all
values and good software should have. We
try to apply that to to this to this
app. Having said that I think the first
launch was not as easy as it could have
been and I guess that makes for a
perfect story for podcast called Lounge.
We had been stuck in review for what was
it like two months, three months?
>> Yeah, I think so. Something like that.
>> Yeah, there was a test fight for a
while. Like we always wanted to have
this out on the app store and of course
there are some doubts because yeah, it
is an app store connect client.
Obviously we do a bit more but
>> there's been other attempts at this
before.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> People who've been in this racket for a
while have seen them come and go and I
know me whenever you said this I was
kind of like well it'll be fun to watch
Hit, you know, sit here and bang his
head against the wall. But like I will
be honest, I did not expect this to
>> actually succeed. Not cuz I didn't think
you could build something useful.
>> I'm here for you, man. Uh not cuz I
didn't think you'd be successful at
building it, but because like
>> I've seen this play out before and it's
like
>> Mhm. Yeah, that's fair.
>> There's a lot of things designed to not
make this necessarily successful. And so
>> I mean, and that's why we were stuck in
review for a long time, right? like
we're at some point like is this ever
going to happen? A worst case we would
talk we just distribute it outside of
the app store. We initially wanted to
launch it at a conference. I think it
was the one in Folkston.
>> Yeah. Swiftcraft I think it was
>> Swiftcraft. Yeah. And then we were stuck
in review still actually. Then we were
even stuck in like a cancelling or in
review cuz it was all weird situation
and then
>> not until like dubdub DC I think.
>> So for context that was Folkston was
early May I believe. Oh yeah. Um, so
just for context, we had submitted by
then and then it got to dubdubdubc and
we were still stuck. So that's at least
like 1 month and over a month.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So DC uh bul makeup I was there
luckily I went to the to the app store
lab that they have there on in in Apple
Park. I had contact with one of the
people from the App Store Connect API uh
luckily and she said, "Oh, you need to
talk to this person to get it sorted."
And then we talked to her. She wrote
down my number and then she listened and
looked at the screen, typed the number,
wrote something down and like, "Oh gosh,
she didn't say a word." And I was like,
"Give me something."
And then um so yeah, it's uh it takes a
long because it's currently stuck in
legal uh because they wanted to make
sure we didn't sell their product. We
didn't sell App Store Connect as a
product necessary. We actually did extra
things and not just literally be App
Store Connect. The name was okay cuz we
have four App Store Connect and as long
as you say it's for something instead of
trying to be that something, it should
be okay. And then I think the next
morning, yeah, the day after see we got
approved.
>> Do you think it was actually gonna go
through anyway? And then it's like, wow,
it may have just been in a giant pile.
>> Well, they will never say so, but it
definitely helped, of course. Like, and
that's why that's why DC is such an
important week in general, I think, to
go to the labs and talk to engineers and
talk to people,
>> talk to Apple. This is the one moment of
the year where you can actually talk to
these people, which is very powerful.
>> What is it? developer support ticket. Is
that what it's called? Where like Apple
developers get two of them a year where
you can talk. The idea is that you can
talk to an engineer. Is there a is there
a mechanism for that for like app review
or app store questions?
>> I don't know. I have never tried
actually. I've never used the idea.
>> The stereotype with those is that you
only get two a year. So developers never
use any because they're afraid to waste
it. Uh, and that's definitely
>> use one next week just to ask how they
are, how they doing
>> cuz so much of the time it's like just
getting a human being inside of the
spaceship to like acknowledge it and
then flag it somewhere like cuz they can
like slack or email somebody. But I
wonder if like if you ever get stuck in
one of those if you could use one of
those to get to get a hold of a person
cuz it just kind of worked for you all
that
>> WWDC happened to be coming up. But if it
had been August like what would you have
done? I've never used one of them, but
it was my first time at dub.dc this year
and I managed to go to the app store
connect API lab and I had about 10 12
questions and they were incredibly kind
to just let me stay after my session as
well and I basically went through all of
the feedback. It was literally like 30
40 minutes with one person was like a
lot better than just me filing feedback
for about and the feedback was important
as well cuz then I could go and say like
look I filed this radar this is all of
like all of the context and I basically
got answers for absolutely everything.
So yeah it was honestly invaluable just
just for that.
Yeah, it's crazy how useful. I mean, I
guess this sounds really obvious on the
surface, but talking to the actual
people instead of just filing into a a
giant, you know, anonymous bucket,
>> uh, it can make a really big difference.
>> So, you got it. It was approved. I
assume in May you had all these plans
for exciting launches and especially
knowing you all which we should get into
at some point. You do crazy things and
so I assume you were very excited about
it in May and then by the time it got to
June it was like it just it's out there
now and like how did that launch itself
go at that point?
>> I think it's very much like every other
launch is like it feels so anticlimactic
like antilimax. It's like okay I guess
this is a thing now.
Um yeah and then then slowly but steady
first users start to dripping in. It
went quite fast quite quickly. Obviously
helped that we both do a lot of public
speaking and a lot of conferences. Um so
we always have like a room full of
potential users uh in front of us. But I
think what we noticed quicker than
anything before is how how much the app
has been promoted by our users, not even
by ourselves. Like every time someone
mentioned App Store Connect in on
Twitter, people would just tag Helm and
say just just use Helm instead. And
that's the best feeling you can have. I
think
>> from the beginning as well, like that
that was it was pretty impressive. like
it was just like yeah we didn't really
have to do obviously we've we've done a
lot but we didn't have to do a lot to
kind of like just promote it and I think
it probably has to do with it's probably
the first time that we have an app where
the target audience is the same as the
audience we've got online anyway like
every time we go to conferences that's
>> the exact audience we want to be hitting
>> so yeah I think that's that's probably
part of it but yeah it's been surprising
that like every week you wake up one day
and it's like someone talking about like
Helm and or someone complains about App
Store Connect. And then in the comments,
it's like, oh, just go use use Helm and
and it's like, oh, we we didn't even
have to jump on that thread. Someone
else did like just set it for us, which
is
>> which is worth 10 times more than
somebody promoting it for
>> it's a great sign.
>> So, what other like marketing things
have you done? So, obviously, uh you
know, you go to conferences, maybe you
make some stickers or pens or something,
but is there anything unique? I'm
laughing and Hit is already he's pulling
something out here. Uh so for the
audience that's just listening, Hit is
holding Yeah. Uh what we in America
would call a jersey what I believe
everywhere else in the world would call
a kit.
>> Is it is a kit the uh is a kit the whole
thing or is that also just the top part?
What's the top part called?
>> In the UK they have like a thousand
words for it here as well. I think some
people call it top, some people call it
kit as well. Like just the the top bit.
I don't know. uh just call it whatever.
It's a uh football or again as Americans
would call it soccer shirt thing that
you'd wear uh while playing the sport
and it has a big helm logo on the front.
As we launched L it took off quite a bit
and Paul was visiting Amsterdam I think
for conference or maybe distressing I
don't know and then we were like ah we
need to do something fun marketing wise
like do something really crazy and then
Paul was collecting football shirts and
it's like oh we could sponsor maybe we
could sponsor like a really low tier and
as soon as he sent that I said you don't
have to tell me more because I knew in
Amsterdam there's an amateur football
club called AFA Swift who means
Amsterdam Football Association Swift. So
the name the football and it was also in
white and blue so it's like on brand.
It's your colors. It has the word swift
in it. And is there any place where you
can find an audience of iOS developers
uh that is more obvious than a low tier
football club in
>> I'm pretty sure we have no downloads
from that.
>> Zero. I think probably web visits but no
downloads. Actually, I had someone on
the conference say to me like, "Oh,
yeah. I I didn't know Hel when I heard
the story about the jerseys. I went to
download it."
>> Nice.
>> Um, but I think I like I said before, I
think I I'm pretty sure the team itself
thinks we're a boating company.
>> You heard him say this. You're like,
"Oh, we got to sponsor this this team."
>> Yeah.
>> What then though? Do you Did you call
them up?
>> Yeah. No, just send an email. Hey, I
want to sponsor one of your teams. And
it's like, okay, great. Which teams? We
have we have this, we have that, we have
this. It's like, well, the lowest one
have swift.
>> We'll have Swift 6, I think, cuz it was
also a point with with Swift language
that was coming out, I think was six.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, it's like, yeah, let's do that one.
And then the cost was actually quite
okay. Was not as high as. So, if you're
listening, great marketing tip. Sponsor
a local football club or any club any
>> I will say like
>> obviously this is not a uh user
acquisition strategy but
>> it does add to the sort of joy and fun
around the brand and like I from the
outside Helm is an app that has I
wouldn't necessarily call it a cult
following but it has a like dedicated
set of users who just love it. it makes
their lives easier, but also it's like
it's fun to be part of the club. And I
think that's why you get so much of the
other people responding to other people
saying, "Hey, you should use Helm."
Because it's like, yes, they're saying
it because it's a tool they like and
enjoy. But also, it's like, "Hey, you
should join our club. This is a fun
thing that I'm also, you know, kind of
part of." And so, I don't know, this is
like really maybe stretching it. But I
do think this is a thing that you can do
that if you're just
vibe coding and playing the MR
maximization game, you're never going to
do something like this. But as an indie
who's just making something sort of
joyful and high craft and trying to
build a loyal user base, I think doing
fun stuff like this, uh,
>> one, it just makes your your life more
joyful, but also I think it does have
some benefits to kind of the brand. You
said the app kind of was taking off. Is
the app able to like sustain you?
>> Well, not fully because it's also we're
with the two of us, so we're splitting
it. Although most of it we just reinvest
in into marketing things or into other
small things like that.
>> What does that mean? Reinvest in the
marketing things. Is this this is just
more teams like
>> swag. Yes. uh also uh open by a lot of
open AI credits just in advance just to
make sure that that those feed because
the AI features are the strong the most
important features in our app. So we
just want to make sure that there's
enough credits on there so to last a
long time. Uh also we have now we have
another person helping us out cuz as we
joined Revenue New a year ago we
realized we would get less time but
that's we'll catch on to that story
later. Um but but then we're like, "Oh,
but let's ask another person that we
trust and know well to come join the the
the ship."
>> Okay. So, it's it's very much in the
like this is a product in your lineup
category. Even if it's kind of the the
bigger one.
>> Yeah. Yeah. For now, it is. Yeah. We
love to make this our full-time thing.
We think we can get there within the
next few years at least because it's
still growing every months quite a lot
because that's the thing with these type
of tools, right? Like the more people
use it, the the faster you grow as long
as it's a very stable line. It's not a
spike, but it's just a very stable
linear line almost.
>> Well, and I would imagine given the user
base that once somebody decides they're
going to use it, it because it's a tool
and it becomes part of your
>> how you work. Uh I imagine your churn is
actually relatively low compared to like
a normal consumer app. Is that has that
borne out?
>> I believe so. Yeah. I mean I I have to
say I don't I don't keep an eye on this
like too too much to be honest. we can
say like the growth has been steady and
I know like over this this year we've
had like less time as well and there
there are some like very complex
features that we've been working on as
well that we believe like are going to
make make a difference and we get a lot
of feedback for features that we don't
have as well. Um and so we kind of like
get a sense of what people want and what
we can do to to kind of like grow in
this sense. So at least from my side I'm
not super obsessed with like the the
analytics of things. I'm more obsessed
with kind of just getting value to to
our users and sometimes that's quite
complicated because of the the nature of
of how it is and all the edge cases that
that we have.
>> Um but I try I try to focus more more on
that than just like trying to look at at
numbers and stuff. So but yeah, we we
have a very clear vision of what we
want, what we where we want to get and
what we have to do to get there. That's
where our focus is. Okay, let's pull on
that thread then because like
>> I think I think we've established the
main marketing channel here is product
and goofy swag more than you know you're
not running influencer ads or anything
like that which for developer tool
probably is the right call. We're now at
like a year and a half that it's been in
the store right uh give or take. So
from that starting point, the initial
version of the app, uh what are kind of
the big features that you've done that
have kind of moved the needle a little
bit?
>> Obviously the biggest one is uh
translations, but we basically had that
from day one. So our goal is that
anywhere in the app or anywhere that you
actually have localized content, you are
able to translate it very very easily
with one click. Um, so basically this is
if you're writing release notes and
you're shipping to multiple stores or
you're writing uh keywords and you want
to translate them to all of your
localizations and all of your product
pages in all of the countries that you
support. Um, you can basically do it
with one one click and you don't have to
actually hire a service or or anything
like that to do that. We use AI to do
it. uh you can use your your own API
key, but we kind of like just provide
support out of the box without having to
do anything. It's just as easy as you
can get just one tap and then you
translate the content. So you've got a
better chance of people actually
downloading your app in those in those
markets.
>> You said this is obviously the biggest
thing. So like based on what you're
hearing from people, this is the biggest
like if I lost this app today, this is
what would make me my work harder or
take longer or whatever. This is also
the main reason why we still don't have
all apps connect features in there today
is because we really really try to look
at each part of AppSto Connect and think
what is currently the the bottleneck in
this workflow like how can we make you
do the same with as little as effort as
possible because in the end we're all
just lazy people like everyone's lazy
everyone likes to do as little as
possible and as fast as possible like
hence the whole AI uh uh boom. Now
that's normal, right? And I feel like
well with everyone launching their app
like actually putting it on the app
store should not feel as painful as it
was. And I think that's how we tackle
every feature like just look at it from
the out with with our developers eyes
and see like okay how can we make this
part better and one of them is like
every every single update from of helm
is shipped with helm as well uh which is
very meta but it's it's also make sure
that we stay on top of things. One of
the reason like why uh we got app clip
support quite early on while so little
people use app clips is because the iOS
app of helm has app clips and otherwise
we couldn't ship helm with helm.
>> So so that's why we added app clip
support so early on already.
>> So speaking of the iOS app that was the
big story when we did our live episode
uh because you were basically launching
it that week like on your one-y year
anniversary you were kind of launching
>> the iOS version. My memory is that the
iOS version was a highly requested
feature.
>> Yeah.
>> But you didn't just take home and make
it to where it works on iOS. You added
like some stuff that was sort of mobile
uh specific. Can you talk about like
>> you know that process of like why you
decided to make an iOS app and then what
you actually did?
Yeah, I think as you said it was it was
highly requested and I think like a lot
of people were saying we even had like
someone come up at the conference and
wanting like a watch OS app so that they
could just um ship their app with one
button on the watch. Uh which is still
probably somewhere in in the road map
but um but yeah I think people want to
do stuff stuff on the go. So, for
example, if you um upload a build and
you don't want to you're about to leave
like the house and you just want to push
something, go to the gym or go for a
walk um and you just want to submit uh
for review while you're waiting for that
to process. You don't have to stay at
home. You can do it on the go. So, that
was the whole the whole plan. So, we
just wanted to do features that made
sense on mobile. We don't we didn't want
to bring everything one for one um to
the iOS app and just do things that make
sense while you're on the go. Um, so you
can view your screenshots, you can, um,
actually submit for review, edit your
release notes, translate, all that, all
that kind of stuff. Um, so that was,
yeah, we also brought a bit of fun to to
to the app as well. As always,
>> we we added like an iOS only feature as
well called Helm Passport because we
were planning to launch it upc and and
for everyone who has been toc knows you
get you talk to a lot of um, developers,
but I don't know. I always find it hard
to remember names, but I always remember
which apps they worked on.
>> Yes.
>> Uh so it's like ah it would be cool to
have like a passport where you can
easily share just a QR code with each
other and then
>> you you get represented in someone
else's passport by the app icon of your
main app. Just that by itself would feel
useless. And so like oh what if you then
can use those stamps to invite them to a
test flight build? uh because it's also
the one opportunity where
>> you meet people that will be running the
next iOS beta on one of their devices
especially if you want to build features
that are specific to the new iOS version
those are 90% of them are like your
developer friends right so um yeah
that's why we decided to to to add that
as a fun little cubistic feature to the
app
>> and that was using app clips right
>> yeah yeah That was that was using app
clips. I think one one of the things we
we thought is if everyone because these
interactions are quite quick with
people. If you are talking and you say
like, "Oh, I want to save your number or
whatever." They're usually quite quick.
So if they have to download the app, set
up the App Store Connect keys and all
that kind of stuff while you're just
talking to them, they're likely just not
to do it. So that's why we decided to do
the app clip so that if you don't have
the app installed, you can still save
the stamp, share the stamp, all that,
all that kind of stuff. And another cool
thing that you can do with with the
passport as well that's that's quite
good and we wanted to fix is that when
you go to these conferences or places
and you share your um your beta group to
add the tester you usually end up with a
lot of anonymous um users um and with
the stamps you always know who is in
your betas um because you save them by
email and name and all that kind of
stuff. So you kind of keep track of who
you invited where and it's it's quite
nice as well
>> cuz you guys go to a lot of conferences.
Have you been using it regularly at at
conferences and has it come in handy in
that way?
>> Yeah, it's also we love to challenge
people. So we give like a a free a free
lifetime subscription or something if
they show us a full passport like the
one with the biggest number gets
lifetime at the end of the conference
something like that. Actually, also when
when someone has your stamp in their
like Charlie stamp in the password, you
unlock a launch FM app.
>> That's right. Yeah, there's a launched
custom icon in Helm. I forgot about
that. Yeah. So, if you see Hitta or poll
anywhere in the world next week as we
record, although I guess it will be in
the past by the time this comes out, hit
will be in in Singapore with me.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, if you travel back in
time, uh,
>> no, that's that's really fun. So that
was that was like a big release based
with a lot of requests. The iOS app
store is a different beast as far as
search traffic and the amount of users
and everything.
>> Did you see that make a bump in terms of
downloads or installs or anything?
>> Like Paul said, we're both not really on
top of our numbers really. We we
>> Yeah, I do remember the iOS app when it
launched. That that's one of the only
things I remember about numbers. Uh it
was a massive spike for the iOS app, but
that's just as we launched it. There was
a massive massive spike. But
>> that's literally news event.
>> As much as you'll you'll get from me for
for numbers. Don't really remember
anything else.
>> Maybe maybe we should
>> I think we should
>> we should build analytics in Helm to
give us an insight where our users come.
Well, I was more just meaning in terms
of the business like you know
>> did that accelerate to the point you had
already uh brought on help so it was
already like you had more people but
like did it increase the numbers where
like you could do more or spend more
money or not work on client work as much
or anything like that?
>> It did give a bit of a boost and I think
yeah well we really don't care about our
numbers honestly. We we should this is
not a business podcast. This is not sub
club. Yeah. Yeah.
We're on here launched for a reason.
We're not in the sub club yet. I think
that's also says something about how we
do our apps. Like we really just care
about quality. We we want to do things
right. And you can always change
business logic later on. And as you
grow, you have more to sell. And
obviously there will be some things
later this year that we will sell for
more money probably. um more focused
towards teams because we noticed more
and more teams are using it. So like
people from sport started using Helm to
respond on Tesla feedback and and
customer reviews. There's got to be some
shift to try to make this more of a
full-time thing. But I think the last
year or so we didn't really feel that
need. We just wanted to have fun and
build fun things. Um obviously yeah we
were also working at VCAT so we didn't
need that that push to try to grow the
business and that was perfect for us to
do in the past year and uh I think this
year 2026 we tried to do it like full
throttle and bring Helm to the to the
next level basically.
>> So I mean speaking of the sort of the
app and quality of the app side of
things there's kind of two two things I
want to talk about. So one is the the
actual technology stack. This is a Mac
app and it's you built it pretty much
all in Swift UI. Is that correct?
>> Yep.
>> This is not exactly welltrodden ground,
especially apps that are not like I
have, you know, some apps that are
pretty lightweight that are Swift UI and
that's fine, but this is an app with
lots of forms and typing in and there's
a lot of windows that can pop up. I
guess one, why? Cuz both of you had
experience with UI kit. Well, I guess
maybe this is the answer. you had
experience with UI kit but probably not
appkit. Uh so I guess the first question
is why and then the second question is
do you regret that or has it been pretty
good?
>> I think Swift UI cuz we're both like
quite like H is very familiar with with
Swift UI anyway and he's like quite
quite good at it. I was more used to
work in a job and in UI kit but for my
other apps and for any other apps it's
always been like Swift UI anyway. So, I
think like that was a pretty obvious um
choice from the beginning. And we've hit
like some snags, but it's not never been
anything that you go like, "Oh, I need
to rewrite my whole app in UI kit." It's
never been something like outrageous
that we've been it's impossible to do.
>> No major roadblocks. I guess to me, the
thing that I would have expected is is
all the like text entry or I don't know.
I feel like I run into weird little bugs
with those types of controls versus just
like buttons and styles and stuff. You
know, Swift UI is great.
>> I think I think Swift UI is great if you
get good at it and it's easier to get
good at it. But I think what a lot of
people forget is that yes, it because it
looks so easy. They forget that it's
like all magical uh straight out of the
box. But there's a difference between
writing good Swift UI code and bad Swift
UI code, right? Like the way how you use
properties and variables and stuff
really change the impact. And then I
think this is also where it shows again
that we make a good team cuz sometimes
we do it next and then Paul jumps in
with all the instruments and he's really
good at instruments and then he finds
that weird little bug. Um, we had one
like a few weeks ago where if you would
scroll like really quickly in the test
flight feedback list, it would just
crash the app and it turned out changing
a lazy fee into a normal fee fixed it.
Swift UI feels like it's easier to get
yourself in trouble in ways that you
can't understand. Whereas like AppKit or
well UI kit anyway in my experience like
it's harder to get to the end but like
you're less likely to end up in a
situation where you totally hosed
yourself in a way that's impossible to
to figure out. So it sounds like Paul
you you kind of have uh quite a bit of
experience of diagnosing these types of
problems.
>> Mhm. Yeah. I think like I used to work
in a company where I spent uh about 6
months just doing performance work and I
think that kind of changed things a lot
and it was like a pretty massive like
app in general. So it was like a lot of
old devices and stuff from users and
like you develop a lot of like skill
sets and I think that's why we always
say like we work very well together like
we've got very different skill sets and
we don't try like to get very good at
what the other does very well. it's like
more like complimentary. So we go like,
"Oh yeah, I'll do this. You do the other
part." That allows us to move like very
fast while still delivering like very
like good quality stuff. But yeah, I
think I think in general like if you're
able to diagnose those those issues and
if you're able to like have the right
tool set to to look into those
performance issues and just try and and
fix them and get past it, you will also
understand a lot of like Swift UI and
what you like shouldn't do in general a
lot more. And we've had like, as I said,
we've had like a few cases where it's
been like, "Oh, this is pretty bad." But
then you just diagnose it, you
eventually find the root cause and
you've learned and you go on the next
one, you won't do it the same way. And
you kind of like just go um go and keep
keep learning um the framework. It's
never been like, oh, we we just need to
stop using it. Um because it's it
doesn't work for us. It's Yeah, it's
been pretty good. And then how you work
together actually was kind of the other
the other part of this question because
it seems like everybody I know that has
a duo like this. It was like this
magical thing that kind of came out of
nowhere and they're like very sympatico.
Was that the case with you? Have you
ever worked both of you? Have you ever
worked with another person like this
before? Not like part of a big team but
just kind of two people who kind of work
together well. We were lucky but that it
matched so well and we just tried it and
of course we had to find our ways of
doing things but I think quite quickly
we came to a structure that works well
which is chaos. Um yeah that so that
actually I I remember this from our live
show. I asked the question expecting to
know the answer of like how do you guys
break up work and I thought it was going
to be like Paul does most of the backend
stuff with the API work and then hit
does most of the front-end stuff
>> and it sounded more like either one of
you is just as likely to pull a ticket
>> and you'll go really far kind of in the
area of your expertise and then the
other person might just jump in to help
but like
>> you both just sort of do everything.
It's not like there's this clear
separation of concerns like you might
expect. No, it's really is depending on
what feature you're working on or you
want to work on and then sometimes I
start a feature and then I make it all
flashy and nice and somewhat work or
give it actual data and sometimes Paul
makes something and then it looks
horrendous and then I jump in to make it
and now even we're to a point like Paul
is not allowed to work on anything else
but inapp purchases and subscriptions
and every time he does he has to pay a
fine
We have good dinner once we launch this.
>> But it seems it does seem really healthy
that it's not like there's areas that
neither that either of you just never
look at. Like you can imagine a lot of
times it's like, "Oh, that's his area. I
never even touched that." But it sounds
like both of you are pretty familiar.
You might do a like mediocre job at the
other person's area and then let the
other person come in and kind of clean
it up. But it kind of creates a scenario
where both of you are familiar with
everything, I'm guessing.
>> Yeah, I think it's also important
because you need to stay familiar with
your own app, right? Like you need to
know your app inside out for to able to
help with support and stuff. Um, and to
know how to scale things. Um, so I think
we'll never be like fully isolated, I
think, because I think it's part of
ownership like we share the ownership.
So we actually share the ownership of
everything as well. So
>> also the less spam birds. So yeah. How
do you handle support?
>> I think for a long time we were dealing
like normal. We had like diagnostics
great package from Anton from in there
to get some logging if if needed. What
we noticed really quickly is that quite
a lot of times we had to ask key okay
can please send the diagnostics um and
then hope for the best.
>> Diagnostics for those listening that's
an SDK for
>> Oh yeah that's an SDK. Yeah, it's a
Swift package and it basically builds up
an HTML page and shows all the error
logs and stuff that well depends what
you log in there really anything you
want
>> and then users can send that to you
through your
>> Yeah, just an HTML file usually email or
whatever you have set up. Yeah, exactly.
And that's Antoine uh Vanderly that
makes that. Yeah. And then I think at
some point I was like ah you know what
this is quite annoying and I think the
whole support experience is also not
really nice uh because it's just an
email and hope for the sake of emailing
that it turns out nicely. Uh so I think
I at least five coded this I think in
like a day or two. I hate the word fico,
but this is it was so much pipe going
on. It was definitely f coloring where I
built like a a back end in superbase uh
quickly with all the fields in there
that of teams that we would want to have
in there. Obviously made like a flashy
nice uh UI that just asks you about your
name and optional email address even I
think and then a message and then you
can add photos to it and that's it.
That's all there is. And then with that
submission, we automatically send the
diagnostics file. So we can just see
what errors that have been thrown and it
gives us a bunch of information like
straight out of the box without having
to email back and forth to the person
like, oh, can you please provide an
example? Okay, please do this. So we can
actually see what errors app store
connect API has been throwing and what
their setup is and stuff. So this is
really just a lowware and we can then
create like a linear ticket straight
from that submission as well. So we can
try try triage it later, I guess.
>> Have you thought about uh you know
wrapping that into a little SAS product
and selling it? Cuz that would be
interesting.
>> Helm support.
>> No, never.
>> Oh, okay. Did I touch on something here?
>> Yeah, not this year probably. But uh
yeah. Yeah, the internal tool is called
Harbor and it has a a similar app icon
as well, but with an anchor instead of a
helm and it has been working well for
us. Um, we're now adding it to our new
app that we're making as well to see how
it would scale to other apps. Uh, but
the idea is probably to at some point
make this our next developer tool. I
think one thing that we learned is that
we probably will stick to two teams that
we love and that's developer tools and
music.
I'm no more guide ser
overlapping uh
>> one for the parents and one for the
nerdy friends.
>> Yeah. So yeah. So maybe who knows but
that has been really helpful I would
say.
>> Do you get much uh support that's like
app store connect issues or do most
people understand that line of like you
know oh this isn't actually the app's
fault. This is, you know, App Store
Connects.
>> We do get like a fair amount of App
Store Connect issues, but I think we've
like we used to get a lot of like weird
uh issues with like entities in App
Store Connect not being okay or 500s and
stuff from the API and we've like we
used to get so much of it um that we
just like improved our networking and
stuff to retry and that kind of solved a
lot of the of the feedback that we have.
Um, but it's always been quite like
developers are a great audience and user
base to have because all the feedback is
so detailed. Like I remember someone who
couldn't they had an issue with the
token or something and they just
literally we didn't reply overnight and
we had like an email chain full of like,
oh, I've tried this. It didn't work. And
then eventually they kind of fixed it
themselves in a way. They were like, oh
yeah, it was my uh VPN or something. I
don't I I don't even know what what it
was to be honest. I don't know how I
would even reproduce it. But yeah, we do
we do get a bunch of of feedback like
that. But it's usually like quite
they're quite understanding um that
sometimes it's an API issue and we
respond to it quite like quickly as
well. So
>> you're not getting a lot of support
tickets that are like why did my app get
rejected?
>> None of that. None of that.
>> And also I think the fact that our user
base knows what an API is already says.
>> Yeah. Exactly. That goes a long way.
>> It's a win already. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Even in in my, you know, uh, much
smaller developer tool, it is funny the
difference in support I get there versus
my consumer app. Like I'll get people
that'll like dig up their Mac activity
logs and send those along and I'm like,
man, I wouldn't even know how to like
ask you to send that to me. Uh, and that
is amazing sometimes. All right. So, I
mean, we're getting close to time, so uh
I'll end this the same way I always end
this show, which is by asking you, uh,
what's a person or people out there that
have inspired you that you'd recommend
others check out? And I'll start with
Paul.
>> I would say anyone in the I think I
mentioned this last time uh in the
podcast we did live. Um, but I would
mention anyone in the uh indie house
that we stay in uh during dubdub every
time. It's an incredible group of
talented people, but if I have to
mention one, I would say Clemens
Straser. Um, got to know him a lot this
year and is honestly such a source of
inspiration. Like literally constant
constant inspiration. So yeah, I would
say that outside of development, I would
one person that um has inspired me a lot
in my life is my my dad. Uh that's
someone I always say. Um, and yeah, I've
always admired how much he turned I'm
quite bad at like dealing with problems
and stuff. I get quite like overwhelmed
and how much he actually just turned
problems into nothing within just a
conversation. He just went like, "Oh,
yeah, that's not an issue." And you felt
immediately safe. That's something that
I always try to take with me and think,
but yeah, I think that's the people I I
would say.
>> I think yeah, obviously also the in your
house because they're great bunch of
people. But another person that I really
admire is Michael Flarup, like a app
icon designer. Um, but also generally
fun guy. Every time I see him, like we
know each other for a long time. We met
at a designer conference like over 12
years ago, I think. And every time I see
him, we're like absolute fun chaos
together. So, I can't wait to see him
again in Finland. I think the last time
I said David Edinburgh. Uh, but
>> Oh, you did. Yeah, you did. You did.
>> Okay. Another one. Another one.
>> You know what? You know what? I'm going
to say Daniel Steinberg cuz I feel like
Daniel Steinberg is a bit the the David
Edinburgh of of of development like full
of knowledge. Everybody loves him and
he's just the nicest guy to everyone.
Like I want to I want to grow up like
Daniel Steinberg I think.
>> Oh man. Yeah. D I haven't had Daniel on
the show. Uh I've had Michael on. He's
one of those people that I don't know
how to say this. Like because he's like
a cool designer person who I followed
online for so long, I kind of expected
him to be a little bit not as nice. Does
that make sense? You know, like he just
seems like elevated. Like he's
>> not all designers are an
>> I've learned this. Uh Sebastian Dwith
was is also in this category. Uh, I
thought he was going to be like this
super cool biker designer dude and then
you meet him and he's like the
friendliest person you've ever met and
you're like, "Oh my gosh." But yeah,
Michael is very much in that category.
He's uh extremely cool and yeah, I guess
he's going to be at Arctic Conf in uh in
Finland. Awesome. Well, uh, thank you
both for doing this with me again. So, I
guess uh where can people find both of
you and your work? We'll start with you,
Ha.
>> at Helm_App. uh is our Twitter handle.
Um I think that's the main main one. Uh
but for myself, it's hit
which is in the show notes cuz it's in
the show notes.
>> Uh oh wait, hit.design is my website.
That's an easy one. Has all the links.
>> There you go.
>> So yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Perfect. And how about you Paul?
>> For me, say madhelm_app.
Uh and then website is paulpierre.dev.
Uh, and then you'll find all the all the
links there as well.
>> Awesome. Well, again, thank you very
much. Thank you all uh for listening. If
you want to find more Launched,
including episodes with most of the
people uh you you mentioned at the end
there, you can find that at
launchfm.com.
And launched FM is our handle basically
everywhere. Uh so you can find that
there. And I'll see you all in 2 weeks.
Thank you so much for listening. You can
find more launched at launched fmm.com
and you can find me on pretty much all
the social medias. I'm @_chucky on
Twitter or charliemchapman pretty much
everywhere else. And of course, huge
thanks to Revenue for making this
episode and all future episodes of
Launch possible. I'll see you all again
in 2 weeks.